Have you ever thought about who owns
JavaScript? The answer may surprise you.
At this point, it feels so common that
it's kind of like asking who owns water.
But if we've learned anything from
Nestle, it's that corporate greed has no
limit. And to make it even worse, the
actual owner of JavaScript didn't create
it, doesn't maintain it, and isn't even
involved in its ongoing development. I
could literally be thrown in prison for
broadcasting the words JavaScript on
screen without the express written
consent of the Oracle Corporation. But
there's one guy who took a look at this
mess and in a stunning act of developer
heroism or sheer boredom, decided to
pick a legal battle against a company
with unlimited resources. In today's
video, we'll break down the crazy battle
to control the JavaScript trademark. It
is August 27th, 2025, and you're
watching the Code Report. Now, I can't
prove it, but I think this whole problem
first started in 1995 when Nicholas Cage
won his first Oscar. At the time,
websites were simple static documents,
and the way you view them was most
likely using the Netscape Navigator
browser. The founder of Netscape, Mark
Andre, had a vision for the web that
made it more than just a way to share
and distribute documents. He envisioned
a more dynamic platform with rich
clientside interactivity. And to achieve
this, you need to put a programming
language inside the browser. And there
was one obvious choice at the time,
Scheme. Developed in the 1970s at MIT,
Scheme was a minimal, lightweight,
embedded dialect of lisp. It's got first
class functions, closures, and dynamic
typing. And there was only one man in
the world up to the challenge of adding
it to Netscape Navigator, Brendan Ike.
By the time he had joined the company on
that vision, Netscape and Sun
Microsystems, the owner of the newly
created awesome programming language,
Java, had made a quote wide-ranging
agreement for product distribution and
technology exchange. That meant the
scheme dream was over and the Java
nightmare was about to begin. However,
they couldn't just put Java in the
browser because the language needed to
be dumbed down enough for web
developers. From there, as the legend
states, in just 10 days, Brennan created
the first version of the language and
called it Mocha. It had the
functionality of Scheme, the object
orientation of Small Talk, and because
of the collaboration with Sun Micros
Systemystems, the syntax of Java.
Eventually, the name Mocha was changed
to livescript, then lives script to
JavaScript as a marketing ploy to ride
the hype train of Java at the time. It's
hard to believe, but back then people
thought Java was a good programming
language. But most importantly, it gave
Sun the legal grounds to trademark the
JavaScript name. Fast forward to today,
and Sun doesn't even exist, as it blew
up in the do-com bubble and sold to
Oracle in 2010, which gave them control
of the JavaScript trademark. Like, have
you ever wondered why the official
language spec for JavaScript is called
ECMAScript? And why is there no
JavaScript conference or JavaScript
newsletter? Well, it's all because of
Larry.
Damn it, Larry. Bananas. Oracle is a
company that's more involved in sailboat
racing than the JavaScript ecosystem and
can choose to sue your ass if you dare
to use the magic word. So, how do we fix
this? Well, it's simple. You build up a
decade of goodwill, then ask them kindly
to release the trademark. And when they
ignore you, you sue them. At least
that's exactly the path Ryan Dull has
taken, the creator of Node.js and
founder of Dino. Ryan wrote an open
letter to Oracle back in 2022 on his
personal blog, claiming the trademark is
a dark cloud looming over the world's
most popular programming language, and
the best value Oracle could derive from
the trademark would be from the goodwill
it receives by granting it to the public
domain. After that was ignored, he
created JavaScript.tm, a more strongly
worded letter that again argued that
Oracle needs to release the trademark
and by this time also included some
legal arguments. In short, it's because
Oracle has never offered a product
called JavaScript and that the term
JavaScript has become so widely used
without any interference from Oracle.
The trademark should be considered
abandoned according to the definition of
title 15 of the United States trademark
code. And oh, by the way, Oracle
actually committed fraud when they
renewed the JavaScript trademark in 2019
by submitting no.js as evidence of
Oracle's use in commerce, a project
which ironically Ryan created and has no
involvement from Oracle. As of today,
this letter has received over 26,000
signatures of support, including one of
them from Brendan Ike himself and many
prominent members of the JavaScript
community, and Oracle has completely
ignored it. This led to Ryan and Dino
formally filing a petition with the
USPTO to cancel the trademark a few
months later in November of 2024. This
forced Oracle to respond after delaying
until after the deadline when they
submitted a partial motion disputing the
fraud claim by saying that the fact they
submitted notice evidence of proof was
irrelevant since they also submitted
another project called Oracle Jet. If we
have any Oracle Jet users in the room,
please raise your hand. But I had never
heard of it and apparently it's a UI
toolkit based on modern JavaScript,
CSS3, and HTML 5. After going back and
forth and paying lawyers to repeat a few
of the same arguments, the trademark
trial and appeal board cited with Oracle
and dismissed Dino's fraud claim is
stating the no.js screenshot isn't fraud
by itself and that fraud will require a
specific false statement or knowledge
and intent to deceive. And just a few
weeks ago, Oracle also addressed the two
other claims, again denying that
JavaScript is a generic term and that
the trademark has been abandoned. So,
what's next? In short, more lawyers.
Both sides will go to Discovery where
they'll set some ground rules and keep
gathering evidence over the next year.
From there, they'll present in the
summer of 2026 with closing arguments
coming later that year, and we should
have a final decision from the
government sometime before January 2027.
Win or lose though, using the JavaScript
trademark freely isn't going to help you
write better code. And that's why you
need to check out Atlassian, the sponsor
of today's video. They just launched the
Rodev CLI, which transforms your
terminal into an AI coding agent that
speeds up your entire workflow. It can
automate repetitive jobs like writing
tests and reviewing pull requests. And
it's intelligent enough to answer
questions about specific repos in your
company's codebase. That's because
unlike most AI tools, Robo is designed
specifically for professional developers
working on large enterprise
applications. And if your team already
uses Atlassian, it works seamlessly with
your Jira tickets and will update
Confluence documentation for you
directly from the terminal. You'll try
out the robo dev beta for free with the
link below. This has been the code
report. Thanks for watching and I will
see you in the next